Wilbur G Downs Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
Wilbur G Downs Archives
1961-1990
ENTAR.001850
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
5
The Archives of Wilbur G Downs.
Downs, Wilbur G.
Biographical Sketch
Wilbur George Downs was a clinical professor of epidemiology and public health at the Yale University School of Medicine and an expert on tropical medicine. As a lieutenant colonel in the Pacific during World War II, Dr. Downs was chief of preventive medicine for the command in Okinawa. He was awarded the Bronze Star and also received several Presidential and military citations for his work with malaria and communicable diseases. After the war he was assigned by the Rockefeller Foundation to direct a malaria-control program in Mexico, where he was among the first to question the use of insecticides like DDT in trying to control the disease. In 1952, Dr. Downs was asked by the Rockefeller Foundation to establish a program in Trinidad investigating arthropod-borne viruses. He founded the Trinidad Regional Virus Laboratory, now the Caribbean Epidemiology Center in Port-of-Spain. There he trained arbovirologists and was part of a team that isolated and characterized more than 35 new viruses. In 1963 he negotiated the move of the Rockefeller Foundation Virus Laboratory from Manhattan to Yale University and became an associate director of the foundation. He was also director of the Yale Arbovirus Research Unit and professor of epidemiology at the Yale University School of Medicine. With his fellow scientists, he continued to isolate and characterize viruses, including the Lassa Fever virus, which was named for the Nigerian village where it originated, and was so virulent that it killed a laboratory worker in 1970, forcing a halt to research. He was a consultant to projects in the Caribbean, Asia and Africa, and a member or chairman of advisory committees for the World Health Organization, the United States Public Health Service, the State Department, the Department of Defense and the National Academy of Sciences. He was born in Perth Amboy, N.J., and graduated from Cornell University in 1935 and from Cornell University Medical College in 1938. He received a Master of Arts from the Johns Hopkins School of Public Heath and Hygiene in 1941. (Excerpted from NY Times Obituary, 20 Feb 1991)
Description of the Material
The archives of Wilbur G Downs include correspondence, lab notes and collecting information.
Connecticut; USA; Correspondence; Notebooks; Drawings; Memorabilia; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- Field & Lab Notes, Series I
  - Drawings & Photographs. Drawings and plates by Wilbur G. Downs. EST number of items = 150+. Some drawings and plates by Shao-Win Ling circa 1938. EST number of objects = 25. In seperate envelope. Estimated number of photographs = 50+., 001853
  - Notebooks. Notebooks containing field and lab information., 001852
- Correspondence, Series II
  Scope and Contents
  Correspondence to and from Wilbur G Downs.
  - Aitken, T.H.G. EST number of items = 5+., 1981-1985; 002391
  - Alexander, Charles. EST number of items = 10+., 1976-1978; 002392
  - Anderson, John. EST number of items = 2., 1976; 002393
  - Anderson, N.H. EST number of items = 2. Oregon State University., 1986; 002394
  - Andrade, Rodrigo. EST number of items = 10+., 1982-1984; 002395
  - Armitage, Brian D. EST number of items = 5. The Caddis Press., 1983; 002396
  - Balslev, Henrik. EST number of items = 1., 1982; 002397
  - Bates, Chip. EST number of items = 3., 1984; 002398
  - Baumann, Richard W. EST number of items = 5+. Brigham Young University., 1975-1988; 002399
  - Bednarik, Andrew. EST number of items = 5+., 1980-1983; 002400
  - Bournaud, Michel. EST number of items = 5., 1986; 002401
  - Boyle, Robert. EST number of items = 5+. Contains newspaper clippings., 1980-1982; 002402
  - Burian, Steve. EST number of items = 2., 1990; 002403
  - Campbell, George. EST number of items = 2. The International Cockroach Society, INC., 1985; 002404
  - Carmichael, Peter. EST number of items = 5., 1961-1963; 002405
  - Clements, A.N. EST number of items = 1., 1966; 002483
  - Danks, H.V. EST number of items = 1., 1977; 002479
  - Denning, Donald G. EST number of items = 5+., 1981-1983; 002406
  - Dodds, Peter. EST number of items = 10+. UCONN., 1976-1981; 002407
  - Dodge, Harold Rodney. EST number of items = 10+., 1962-1973; 002408
  - Edmonds, George F. EST number of items = 5+., 1976-1977; 002409
  - Ehlert, Fred. EST number of items = 1., 1982; 002478
  - Elliot, Sarah M. EST number of items = 5., 1987; 002410
  - Epler, John H. EST number of items = 2., 1990; 002411
  - Fisher, Ben. EST number of items = 1., 1979; 002477
  - Flint, Oliver. EST number of items = 10+. National Museum of Natural History., 1981-1985; 002412
  - Godwin, Bert. EST number of items = 10+., 1985-1989; 002413
  - Gordon, Elizabeth. EST number of items = 10+., 1975-1985; 002414
  - Grant, Peter M. EST number of items = 1., 1990; 002480
  - Greene, Charles. EST number of items = 2., 1990; 002415
  - Hamilton, Steven. EST number of items = 15+., 1980-1982; 002416
  - Herrmann, Scott. EST number of items = 5., 1980-1982; 002417
  - Hevel, Gary F. EST number of items = 1., 1984; 002418
  - Holzenthal, R. EST number of items = 1., 1988; 002484
  - Hutchinson, Evelyn G. EST number of items = 5., 1983; 002419
  - Kitzmiller, Jim. EST number of items = 2., 1984-1984; 002420
  - Kondratieff, Boris. EST number of items = 3., 1982; 002421
  - Krinsky, Bill. EST number of items = 5+., 1986-1987; 002422
  - La Fontaine, Gary. EST number of items = 1., 1984; 002474
  - Larson, David. EST number of items = 1., 1986; 002473
  - Lavigne, Robert. EST number of items = 1., 1984; 002472
  - Lehmkuhl, Dennis. EST number of items = 2., 1975; 002423
  - Malicky, Hans. EST number of items = 1., 1986; 002471
  - Manuel, Kenneth L. EST number of items = 1., 1983; 002482
  - Martinez, Lee Anne. EST number of items = 1., 1986; 002424
  - McCafferty, W.P. EST number of items = 2., 1984; 002425
  - Miller, William. EST number of items = 1., 1977; 002470
  - Morse, John. EST number of items = 3., 1983; 002426
  - Nelson, Vernon. EST number of items = 25+., 1983-1990; 002427
  - Nimmo, Andrew P. EST number of items = 1., 1988; 002481
  - Passante, Jeff. EST number of items = 3., 1983-1984; 002428
  - Pizzuto, Ernest. EST number of items = 1., 1983; 002469
  - Pratt, Harry D. EST number of items = 5+., 1984-1986; 002429
  - Price, Joan. EST number of items = 3., 1977-1981; 002430
  - Rajagopalan, P.K. EST number of items = 2., 1983; 002431
  - Remington, Charles. EST number of items =20+., 1979-1987; 002432
  - Ross, Ed. EST number of items = 1., 1980; 002468
  - Ruiter, Dave. EST number of items = 15+., 1984-1990; 002433
  - Schaefer, Carl W. EST number of items = 3., 1984; 002434
  - Schmid, F. EST number of items = 5+., 1980; 002435
  - Schneider, Katherine. EST number of items = 2., 1990; 002436
  - Sherk, Truman. EST number of items = 5+., 1983-1988; 002437
  - Shusda, Ed. EST number of items = 1., 1983; 002438
  - Souza Lopes, Hugo. EST number of items = 5+., 1976-1982; 002439
  - Stinson, Bill. EST number of items = 2., 1986; 002440
  - Subak-Sharpe, H. EST number of items = 1., 1961; 002475
  - Unknown. Correspondance between Wilbur G. Downs and an unknown reciever/sender due to illegible signiture or no name at all. EST number of items = 5+., 002485
  - Unzicker, John D. EST number of items =10+., 1978-1979; 002441
  - Weir, John M. EST number of items =2., 1980; 002442
  - Welling, Eduardo C. EST number of items =2., 1982-1983; 002443
  - Wiggins, Glenn B. EST number of items =5+., 1978-1988; 002444
  - Wills-Flowers, R. EST number of items = 1., 1977; 002476
  - Yekel, Steve. EST number of items =1., 1980; 002445
- United States Army, Series III
  - Awards. Documentation, pictures, and some badges of awards and honors that Wilbur G. Downs was decorated with for recognition of his service in the U.S. Army., 002449
  - Fiscal Information. Fiscal reports, pay and allowance acounts, reciepts etc from Wilbur G. Downs time in the U.S. army., 1943-1946; 002450
  - G.I. Certificates of service and clearance as well as other miscellaneous general information on Wilbur G. Downs service in the U.S. army., 002447
  - Orders. Orders and official appointment information from the war department and military district Regarding Wilbur G. Downs., 1942-1945; 002448
- Biographicals, Series IV
  A collection of biogrophies kept by Wilbur G. Downs on many friends and colleagues.
  - Biology. Biographies kept by Wilbur G. Downs on biology, entomology and other natuaral history associated colleagues., 002453
  - Medical. Biographies kept by Wilbur G. Downs on medical and paramedical colleagues., 002452
- Collection Information, Series V
  Information on the collecting process and identification of specimens Wilbur G. Downs collected while working for the Yale Peabody Museum depatrment of Entomology.
  - Collectors License., 1981-1985; 002455
  - Identification. Information on specimen identicication, cross identification, localiy info, etc., 002458
  - Miscellaneous. Miscellanious archives such as drawings from class room visits and a Caddis Fly song., 002467
  - Pinned Specimens. Pinned specimen information., 1976-1977; 002457
  - Protocol. Wilbur G. Downs protocol for collecting,., 002456
  - Reference Check List., 002466
- Ultra Violet Light Trap Collecting, 1986-1990; Series VI
  - 1986. Ultra violet light collecting information from 1986. EST number of items= 75+., 002460
  - 1987. Ultra violet light collecting information from 1987. EST number of items= 75+., 002461
  - 1988. Ultra violet light collecting information from 1988. EST number of items= 30+., 002462
  - 1989. Ultra violet light collecting information from 1988. EST number of items= 50+., 002463
  - 1990. Ultra violet light collecting information from 1990. EST number of items= 50+., 002464